Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 63: Neurological Disorders.
Central Nervous System Imaging Headache Seizure Disorders Cerebrovascular Diseases Demyelinating Or Degenerative Diseases Neuropathies Spinal Cord Injury Idiopathic Intracranial Hypertension Maternal Ventricular Shunts Maternal Brain Death References Many neurological disorders precede pregnancy.
Most affected women will have successful perinatal outcomes, although some disorders carry specific risks.
Other women will have new-onset neurological symptoms during pregnancy, and these must be distinguished from pregnancy complications.
Neurovascular disorders are an important cause of maternal mortality and accounted for more than 7 percent of maternal deaths in the United States from 2007 through 2016 .
Psychiatric disorders can manifest with cognitive and neuromuscular abnormalities and should be considered in the evaluation of neurological symptoms.
Central Nervous System Imaging.
Computed tomography (CT) and magnetic resonance (MR) imaging assist in the diagnosis, classification, and management of many neurological disorders.
As discussed in Chapter 49, (p. 873), these can be used safely during pregnancy (Chansakul, 2017; Lum, 2020).
CT scanning is often used when rapid diagnosis is necessary and is excellent for detecting recent hemorrhage.
That said, MR imaging is often preferred and is particularly helpful to diagnose demyelinating diseases, arteriovenous malformations (AVMs), congenital and developmental nervous system abnormalities, posterior fossa lesions, and spinal cord diseases .
Whenever either modality is employed, a woman with advanced pregnancy should be positioned in a lateral tilt with a wedge under one hip to prevent hypotension and to diminish aortic pulsations, which may degrade the image.
Cerebral angiography with contrast injection, usually via the femoral artery, is a valuable adjunct to the diagnosis and treatment of some cerebrovascular diseases.
Fluoroscopy delivers more radiation but can be performed with abdominal shielding.
Positron emission tomography (PET) and functional MR imaging (fMRI) have not been evaluated in detail for use in gravidas (van den Heuvel, 2016).
Headache.
In one national survey in the United States in 2012, 17 percent of persons aged 18 to 44 years reported a severe headache or migraine within the past 3 months .
Burch and coworkers (2015) reported that 24 percent of nonpregnant women in this age group were similarly affected.
Of pregnant women presenting with headache who received a neurological consultation, two thirds were due to primary disorders.
The diagnosis was migraine in more than 90 percent.
Of the other third due to secondary conditions, more than half stemmed from hypertensive disorders .
In one recent observational study at University of Texas Southwestern’s Clements University Hospital, 20 percent of emergency department postpartum visits were for headache .
The classification by the International Headache Society (2018) is shown in Table 63-1.
As discussed, in pregnant women, primary headaches are more common than those derived from secondary causes .
Migraine headaches are those most likely to be affected by the hormonal changes of pregnancy .
The incidences of different etiologies of severe headaches in pregnancy are shown in Figure 63-1 .
Table 63-1.
Headache Classification Figure 63-1.
Incidences of headache causes in 140 consecutive pregnant women for whom inhospital neurology consultation was requested.
# Tension Headache.
These are the most frequent cause of all headaches.
They may be episodic or chronic.
Their characteristic muscle tightness and mild to moderate pain in the back of the neck and head can persist for hours.
Importantly, neurological disturbances or nausea are typically absent, which distinguishes them from migraines.
The pain usually responds to rest, massage, local heat or ice, nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), or mild tranquilizers.
Hospital admission is seldom necessary.
For chronic headaches, amitriptyline can be effective .
# Migraine Headache.
This is a
periodic, sometimes incapacitating neurological disorder with episodic attacks of severe headache and autonomic nervous system dysfunction (Ashina, 2020; Charles, 2017).
The International Headache Society (2018) classifies three migraine types based on chronicity and on the presence or absence of an aura.
1. Migraine without aura-formerly termed common migraine-is characterized by a unilateral throbbing headache, nausea and vomiting, or photophobia.
2. Migraine with aura-formerly termed classic migraine-has similar symptoms preceded by premonitory neurological phenomena such as visual scotoma or hallucinations.
A third of patients have this type, which sometimes can be averted if medication is taken at the first premonitory sign.
3. Chronic migraine is defined by a migraine headache occurring at least 15 days each month for more than 3 months.
Migraine headaches may begin in childhood, peak in adolescence, and tend to diminish in both frequency and severity with advancing years.
According to Ashina (2020), their annual prevalence is 15 percent in women and 6 percent in men.
Another 5 percent of women have probable migraine, that is, they have all criteria but one.
These headaches are especially common in young women and have been linked to hormone levels (Burch, 2020; Charles, 2017).
Sensory sensitivity with migraines is likely caused by monoaminergic sensory control systems in the brainstem, hypothalamus, and cortex .
The exact pathophysiology is uncertain, but symptoms develop when neuronal dysfunction leads to decreased cortical blood flow, activation of vascular and meningeal nociceptors, and stimulation of trigeminal sensory neurons.
Importantly, migraines are not primarily a vascular disorder .
Migraine headaches—especially those with aura in young women—are associated with increased risk for ischemic strokes .
Other associated conditions are asthma, anxiety and depression, and other pain disorders.
Migraine in Pregnancy Migraine headaches are frequently encountered during pregnancy.
Most migraineurs have improvement during pregnancy .
Still, migraines—usually those with an aura—occasionally appear for the first time during pregnancy.
Pregnant women with preexisting migraine symptoms may have other symptoms that suggest a more serious disorder, and new neurological symptoms should prompt a complete evaluation .
Migraines during pregnancy are associated with increased rates of preeclampsia, gestational hypertension, preterm birth, and other cardiovascular morbidities that include ischemic stroke (Grossman, 2017; Wabnitz, 2015).
Bushnell and associates (2009) identified a migraine incidence during pregnancy of 185 cases per 100,000 deliveries.
Of diagnoses associated in these gravid migraineurs, risks were significantly higher for stroke, 16-fo1d; myocardial infarction, fivefold; and heart disease, venous thromboembolism, and preeclampsia/gestational hypertension, each twofold.
In a systematic review of 14 studies, risks for preeclampsia and low-birthweight neonates were significantly increased .
Management Several effective medications are shown in Table 63-2.
Mild headaches respond to oral therapy in 50 to 70 percent of cases.
Initial therapy with acetaminophen or an NSAID, along with an antiemetic, usually suffices for many early headaches.
For severe headaches, parenteral therapy is indicated .
Multitargeted drug therapy is necessary in most cases for migraine relief .
Headaches are treated aggressively with intravenous hydration, parenteral antiemetics, and triptans, and opioids are reserved for the most recalcitrant headaches.
Although a 2-g infusion of magnesium sulfate has gained favor in the past few years, a metaanalysis reported no benefits .
Ergotamine derivatives are potent vasoconstrictors and are avoided in pregnancy because of their uterotonic effects .
Table 63-2.
Medications for Treatment of Acute Migraine in Pregnancy Triptans are serotonin 5-HT1B/2D-receptor agonists that effectively relieve headaches, nausea, and vomiting and greatly reduce analgesic needs.
Triptans can be given as an
oral tablet, injection, rectal suppository, or intranasal spray.
They are best used in combination with NSAIDs .
However, chronic NSAID use is avoided in pregnancy, especially later pregnancy because of fetal ductus arteriosus constriction and fetal urine production decline .
The greatest triptan experience is with sumatriptan (Imitrex), and although not studied extensively in pregnancy, it is not a major teratogen (Saldanha, 2021; Spielmann, 2018).
However, in one study at 36 months of children exposed to triptans in pregnancy, Wood and colleagues (2016) found neurodevelopment differences, including emotionality and activity problems.
Some women will benefit from peripheral nerve blocks, and Govindappagari and coworkers (2014) described their experiences with 13 pregnant women.
For women with frequent migraine headaches, oral prophylactic therapy is warranted.
Amitriptyline (Elavil), 10 to 175 mg daily; propranolol (Inderal), 40 to 120 mg daily; or metoprolol (Lopressor, Toprol), 25 to 100 mg daily, are successful options (Contag, 2010; Lucas, 2009).
Calcitonin gene-related peptide (CGRP) receptor antagonists to prevent migraines have garnered enthusiasm.
Several of these monoclonal antibodies have been approved since 2018 for clinical use but not evaluated in pregnancy (Ashina, 2020; Tepper, 2018).
Similarly, in a Cochrane review, botulinum toxin type A for chronic migraine may reduce migraine days per month by 2 days compared with placebo .
# Cluster Headache.
This rare primary headache disorder is characterized by severe unilateral lancinating pain radiating to the face and orbit, lasting 15 to 180 minutes, and occurring with autonomic symptoms and agitation.
Pregnancy does not affect symptom severity.
Affected women should avoid tobacco and alcohol.
Acute management includes 100-percent oxygen therapy and sumatriptan given as a 6-mg dose subcutaneously .
If recurrent, prophylaxis employs verapamil.
Seizure Disorders.
After headaches, seizures are the next most prevalent neurological condition encountered in pregnancy.
The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention reported that 3 million adults in 2015 had active epilepsy .
Less than half were seizure free in the past year.
Importantly, epilepsy accounted for 5 percent of maternal deaths in the United Kingdom from 2011 to 2013 .
# Pathophysiology.
A seizure is a transient combination of signs and symptoms stemming from abnormal excessive or synchronous neuronal activity in the brain .
Some identifiable causes of convulsive disorders in young adults include head trauma, alcohol- and other drug-induced withdrawals, cerebral infections, brain tumors, biochemical abnormalities, and arteriovenous malformations.
A search for these is prudent with a newonset seizure disorder in a pregnant woman.
The diagnosis of idiopathic epilepsy is one of exclusion.
# Classification.
Epilepsy encompasses different syndromes whose cardinal feature is a predisposition to recurrent unprovoked seizures.
The International League Against Epilepsy recently updated the following definitions .
Main categories describe seizure onset and include focal, generalized, and unknown groups.
Focal seizure onset describes those that originate in one localized brain area and affect correspondingly localized neurological function.
They are believed to result from trauma, abscess, tumor, or perinatal factors, although a specific lesion is rarely demonstrated.
Seizures may occur with either intact or impaired awareness.
Focal seizures without dyscognitive features start in one region of the body and progress toward other ipsilateral areas of the body and produce tonic and then clonic movements.
Seizures can affect sensory function or produce autonomic dysfunction or psychological changes.
Cognitive function is not impaired, and recovery is rapid.
Focal seizures with dyscognitive features are often preceded by an aura and followed by impaired awareness manifested by sudden behavioral arrest or motionless stare.
Involuntary movements such as picking motions or lip smacking are common.
Generalized seizure
onset describes those that involve both brain hemispheres and may be preceded by an aura before an abrupt loss of consciousness.
They may be motor or nonmotor.
There is a strong hereditary component.
In generalized tonic-clonic seizures, loss of consciousness is followed by tonic contraction of the muscles and rigid posturing, and then by clonic contractions of all extremities while the muscles gradually relax.
Return to consciousness is gradual, and the patient may remain confused and disoriented for several hours.
Absence seizures—also called petit mal seizures—are a form of generalized epilepsy that involve a brief loss of consciousness without muscle activity and are characterized by immediate recovery of consciousness and orientation.
Unknown seizure onset describes seizures with an unwitnessed onset.
Thus, they remain unclassified as to focal or generalized onset until further information allows categorization.
However, these can be further subgrouped as motor or nonmotor, or unclassified.
# Preconceptional Counseling.
Women with epilepsy ideally are counseled before pregnancy, and relevant points are presented also in Chapter 9 (p. 166).
Oral folic acid supplementation with 0.4 mg per day is begun at least 1 month before conception.
The dose is increased to 4 mg when the woman taking antiepileptic medication becomes pregnant.
These medications are assessed and adjusted with a goal of monotherapy using the least teratogenic medication.
If this is not feasible, attempts are made to reduce the number of medications and to use the lowest effective dose (Stephen, 2019; Tomson, 2019b).
Medication withdrawal should be considered if a woman is seizure free for 2 years or more.
# Pregnancy Complications.
The major pregnancy-related risks to women with epilepsy are fetal malformations and convulsions.
Seizure control is a priority to avoid its attendant morbidity and mortality.
Early studies described worsening seizure activity during pregnancy, however, this is less common now because of more effective drugs .
Contemporary studies cite higher rates of seizure activity in only 20 to 30 percent of gravidas .
Women who are seizure free for at least 9 months before conception will likely remain so during pregnancy .
Greater seizure frequency is often associated with subtherapeutic anticonvulsant serum levels, a lower seizure threshold, or both.
Numerous pregnancy-associated alterations can result in subtherapeutic serum levels.
These include nausea and vomiting, slower gastrointestinal motility, antacid use that diminishes drug absorption, pregnancy hypervolemia offset by protein binding, induction of hepatic enzymes such as cytochrome oxidases, placental enzymes that metabolize drugs, and increased glomerular filtration that hastens drug clearance.
Importantly, some women discontinue medication because of teratogenicity concerns.
Last, the seizure threshold can be affected by pregnancy-related sleep deprivation and by hyperventilation and pain during labor .
Status epilepticus is a medical emergency.
It is more likely to occur in women with refractory epilepsy .
In a randomized trial of 384 nonpregnant patients with benzodiazepine-refractory status, intravenous levetiracetam, fosphenytoin, or valproate yielded similar results .
Only one half of patients in each cohort had cessation of seizures and improved alertness by 60 minutes.
In addition to seizure-control challenges, women with epilepsy have a small increased risk of pregnancy complications that include miscarriage, hemorrhage, hypertensive disorders, placental abruption, preterm birth, fetalgrowth restriction, and cesarean delivery (Salman, 2018; Viale, 2015).
Importantly, MacDonald (2015) also reports a tenfold higher maternal death rate, and, as mentioned earlier, epilepsy accounted for 5 percent of maternal deaths in the United Kingdom.
Postpartum depression rates also are increased in epileptic women .
Last, children of epileptic mothers have a 10-percent risk of developing a seizure disorder.
With embryofetal malformations, it was difficult for years to
separate the influence of epilepsy from that of its therapy as the primary cause.
Now, untreated epilepsy is thought not to be associated with an elevated fetal malformation rate .
That said, the fetus of an epileptic mother who takes certain anticonvulsant medications has an indisputably greater risk for congenital malformations.
Moreover, monotherapy is associated with a lower rate of birth defects compared with multiagent therapy.
Adherence to these principles has resulted in declining malformation rates from antiepileptic drugs .
Specific drugs, when given alone, raise the malformation rate .
Some are listed in Table 63-3.
Phenytoin and phenobarbital increase the major malformation rate two- to threefold above baseline (Perucca, 2005; Thomas, 2008).
Valproate is a particularly potent teratogen, which has a dose-dependent effect and raises the malformation risk four- to eightfold (Klein, 2014; Tomson, 2019b).
Valproate is also associated with lower cognitive performance .
In general, with polytherapy, the risk rises with each drug added.
A metaanalysis of 31 studies found lamotrigine and levetiracetam to carry the lowest malformation risk .
Table 63-3.
Teratogenic Effects of Common Anticonvulsant Medications # Management in Pregnancy.
The American Academy of Neurology and the American Epilepsy Society have guidelines regarding treatment in pregnancy (Harden, 2009a,b,c).
The major goal is seizure prevention.
To accomplish this, treatment for nausea and vomiting is provided, seizure-provoking stimuli are avoided, and medication compliance is emphasized.
The fewest necessary anticonvulsants are given at the lowest dosage needed for seizure control.
Although some providers routinely monitor serum drug levels, these concentrations may be unreliable because of altered protein binding.
Free or unbound drug levels, although perhaps more accurate, are not widely available.
Importantly, no evidence suggests that such monitoring improves seizure control .
For these reasons, drug levels may be most informative if measured following seizures or if noncompliance is suspected.
For women taking anticonvulsant drugs, a targeted sonographic examination in midpregnancy is recommended to evaluate for anomalies.
Testing to assess fetal well-being is generally not indicated for women with uncomplicated epilepsy.
For women desiring to breastfeed, data regarding the safety of the various anticonvulsant medications are limited.
However, no obvious deleterious effects, such as long-term cognitive issues, have been reported (Birnbaum, 2020; Briggs, 2022).
Of birth control methods, combination oral contraceptive (COC) pill failure rates are higher with some of the anticonvulsant agents.
For example, lamotrigine efficacy is substantially lowered by COCs.
Thus, other more reliable methods should be considered .
Cerebrovascular Diseases.
Abnormalities of the cerebrovascular circulation include both ischemic and hemorrhagic strokes and anatomical anomalies, such as AVMs and aneurysms.
Cerebral ischemia is caused by reduction in blood flow that lasts longer than several seconds.
Early, neurological symptoms may manifest.
After a few minutes, however, infarction often follows.
Hemorrhagic stroke is caused by bleeding directly into or around the brain.
It produces symptoms by its mass effect, by blood’s toxic effects, or by elevated intracranial pressure.
Strokes in nonpregnant women are predominately ischemic.
In gravidas, roughly half are ischemic, and the other half are hemorrhagic .
The obesity endemic in this country, along with a concomitant rise in rates of heart disease, hypertension, and diabetes, has increased the prevalence of strokes.
Compared with men, women have a higher lifetime risk of stroke and associated mortality rate (Martinez-Sånchez, 2011; Virani, 2021).
Moreover, pregnancy raises the immediate and lifetime risk of both ischemic stroke and hemorrhagic stroke (Jamieson, 2010; Jung, 2010).
With an incidence of 10 to 40 cases per 100,000 births, stroke is relatively uncommon in gravidas.
However, it contributes disparately to
maternal mortality rates (Leffert, 2016; Pacheco, 2019; Elgendy, 2021).
The incidence is rising as measured by pregnancy-related hospitalizations for stroke (Callaghan, 2008; Kuklina, 2011).
Most events are associated with hypertensive disorders or heart disease.
Of the pregnancy-related mortality rate in the United States from 2007 to 2016, 7.2 percent was due to cerebrovascular accidents, and 7.8 percent was associated with hypertension .
Of maternal deaths after 42 days postpartum, 9.8 percent were attributable to stroke .
# Risk Factors.
Most strokes in pregnancy manifest either during labor and delivery or in the puerperium.
In a study of 2850 pregnancy-related strokes, approximately 10 percent developed antepartum, 40 percent intrapartum, and 50 percent postpartum .
Of 145 ischemic strokes, Leffert (2016) reported a timing of 45 percent antepartum, 3 percent intrapartum, and 53 percent postpartum.
Several risk factors both unrelated and related to pregnancy have been recognized.
Unrelated causes are age; migraines, hypertension, obesity, and diabetes; cardiac disorders such as endocarditis, valvular prostheses, and patent foramen ovale; and smoking.
Stroke etiologies related to pregnancy include hypertensive disorders, gestational diabetes, obstetrical hemorrhage, and cesarean delivery.
By far, the most common is pregnancy-associated hypertensive disorders.
A third of strokes are associated with gestational hypertension, and hypertensive women compared with normotensive counterparts have a three- to eightfold greater risk of stroke (Scott, 2012; Wang, 2011).
Stroke is the major cause of maternal mortality associated with preeclampsia .
Moreover, women with preeclampsia undergoing general anesthesia may be at higher risk of stroke compared with those given neuraxial anesthesia .
Cesarean delivery raises the peripartum stroke risk 1.5-fold compared with vaginal delivery .
Sepsis from any source increases the risk for postpartum stroke .
Pregnancy-induced effects on cerebrovascular hemodynamics include enhanced autoregulation that maintains blood flow despite changes in systemic blood pressure (van Teen, 2016).
Although cerebral blood flow decreases by 20 percent from midpregnancy until term, it increases significantly with gestational hypertension (Zeeman, 2003, 2004b).
Such hyperperfusion at least intuitively would be dangerous for women with certain vascular anomalies.
# Ischemic Stroke.
Acute occlusion or embolization of an intracranial blood vessel causes cerebral ischemia, which may result in death of brain tissue .
The more commonly associated etiologies of ischemic stroke are shown in Table 63-4.
A transient ischemic attack (TIA) is caused by reversible ischemia, and symptoms usually last less than 24 hours.
Approximately 10 percent of these patients have a stroke by 1 year .
Figure 63-2.
Illustrations of a brain showing various types of strokes seen in pregnancy: (1) subcortical infarction (preeclampsia), (2) hypertensive hemorrhage, (3) aneurysm, (4) embolism or thrombosis in middle cerebral artery, (5) arteriovenous malformation, and (6) cortical vein thrombosis.
Table 63-4.
Some Associated Disorders or Causes of Ischemic and Hemorrhagic Strokes During Pregnancy or the Puerperium Stroke usually incites sudden severe headache, hemiplegia, or other neurological deficits.
Seizures occasionally develop.
Immediate assessment and CT scanning is indicated .
Further evaluation includes echocardiography and additional cranial imaging with CT, MR imaging, or angiography.
Serum lipids are measured with the caveat that their values are distorted by normal pregnancy (Appendix, p. 1231).
Tests to detect antiphospholipid antibodies, lupus anticoagulant, other thrombophilias, and, if indicated, sickle-cell syndromes are performed .
These underlie up to a third of ischemic strokes in otherwise healthy young women.
With a thorough evaluation, most causes of embolism can be identified.
Some of these include cardiac-associated embolism, vasculitis, or vasculopathy such as Moyamoya disease (Miyakoshi, 2009; Pacheco, 2019).
Outcomes of embolic strokes are reported to be favorable and similar to those of nonpregnant women .
For some, thrombolysis for ischemic stroke during pregnancy should be considered .
However, published experiences are sparse .
For some, mechanical thrombectomy can be used.
Preeclampsia Syndrome In reproductive-age women, a significant proportion of pregnancy-related ischemic strokes are caused by gestational hypertension and preeclampsia (Miller, 2020; Zofkie, 2018).
As shown in Figure 63-2, areas of subcortical edema and petechial hemorrhage may progress to cerebral infarction (Aukes, 2007, 2009; Zeeman, 2004a).
Although these usually clinically manifest by an eclamptic convulsion, a few women will suffer a symptomatic stroke from a larger cortical infarction .
Other conditions with findings similar to preeclampsia are thrombotic microangiopathies and the reversible cerebral vasoconstriction syndrome .
The latter, also termed postpartum angiopathy, can cause extensive cerebral edema, necrosis and widespread infarction, and areas of hemorrhage (Edlow, 2013; Miller, 2016).
Cerebral Embolism These strokes usually involve the middle cerebral artery (see Fig. 63-2).
The diagnosis can be made with confidence only after thrombosis and hemorrhage are excluded and is more certain if an embolic source is identified.
Hemorrhage may be more difficult to exclude because both embolization and thrombosis can be followed by hemorrhagic infarction.
Paradoxical embolism is an uncommon cause, even considering that more than a fourth of adults have a patent foramen ovale.
Through the defect, rightsided venous thromboemboli are deported .
Foraminal closure may not improve outcomes in these patients, however, this procedure has been performed during pregnancy .
Assorted cardioembolic causes of stroke include arrhythmias—especially atrial fibrillation, valvular lesions, mitral valve prolapse, mural thrombus, infective endocarditis, and peripartum cardiomyopathy.
Management of embolic stroke in pregnancy consists of supportive measures and antiplatelet therapy.
Thrombolytic therapy and anticoagulation in pregnancy are controversial .
Cerebral Artery Thrombosis Most thrombotic strokes affect older individuals and are caused by atherosclerosis, especially of the internal carotid artery.
Many are preceded by one or more TIAs.
Thrombolytic therapy with a recombinant tissue plasminogen activator (rtPA) is recommended.
Alteplase is one of these.
It is given intravenously within the first 3-hour window if neurological deficits are noted and if neuroimaging has excluded hemorrhage .
A principal risk is hemorrhagic transformation of an ischemic stroke.
This agent can be used in pregnancy, but published experiences of rtPA in this group are few .
Cerebral Venous Thrombosis In one study in the United States, 6 percent of cerebral venous thromboses were associated with pregnancy .
However, in more than 8 million deliveries from the Nationwide Inpatient Sample, cerebral venous thrombosis caused only 2 percent of pregnancy-related strokes .
Predisposing causes are numerous, and for gravidas, late pregnancy and the puerperium are times of greatest risk .
Thrombosis of the lateral or superior sagittal venous sinus usually occurs in the puerperium and often in association with preeclampsia, sepsis, or thrombophilia (see Fig. 63-2).
It is more common in patients with inherited thrombophilias or antiphospholipid antibodies.
Headache is the most frequent presenting symptom, neurological deficits are common, and up to a third of women have seizures .
Oh and colleagues (2020) described a postpartum case in which cerebral vein thrombosis was misdiagnosed as postdural puncture headache.
The diagnosis is made using MR venography.
Management includes anticonvulsants for seizures, and anticoagulation with heparin (Pacheco, 2019; Smith, 2018).
Antimicrobials are given for septic thrombophlebitis, and fibrinolytic therapy is reserved for those women failing systemic anticoagulation.
The acute prognosis for venous thrombosis in gravidas is better than in nonpregnant
subjects, and mortality rates are <10 percent (McCau11ey, 2011).
In women with a prior cerebral venous thrombosis, one systematic review found only one recurrence in 217 pregnancies and five noncerebral venous thrombotic events in 186 pregnancies .
In a study of 52 women on prophylactic anticoagulation with prior cerebral venous thrombosis, recurrent thrombosis or bleeding did not develop.
However, 24 percent had late obstetrical complications .
Ischemic Stroke Recurrence Women with prior ischemic stroke have a low risk for recurrence during a subsequent pregnancy unless a specific, persistent cause is identified.
During a 5-year follow-up of 441 reproductive-aged women with prior ischemic stroke or cerebral venous thrombosis, 13 had a recurrent ischemic stroke, and only two were associated with pregnancy.
The authors concluded that the risk of stroke recurrence is low and a previous ischemic stroke is not a contraindication to pregnancy .
In one study of nonpregnant women, the ischemic stroke recurrence rate was similar between those with and without antiphospholipid antibodies as long as the former received warfarin or aspirin .
The recurrence rate of reversible cerebral vasoconstriction syndrome in a subsequent pregnancy was noted to be 9 percent .
Currently, no firm guidelines define prophylaxis in pregnant women with a stroke history .
The American Heart Association stresses the importance of controlling risk factors such as hypertension and diabetes .
As discussed in Chapters 52 and 55, those with antiphospholipid syndrome or certain cardiac conditions should be considered for prophylactic anticoagulation.
For most of these women, lowdose aspirin given throughout pregnancy seems reasonable.
# Hemorrhagic Stroke.
Intracerebral Hemorrhage The symptoms of a hemorrhagic stroke are similar to those of an ischemic stroke, and their differentiation is possible only with CT or MR imaging (Hemphill, 2015; Smith, 2018).
The two distinct categories of spontaneous intracranial bleeding are subarachnoid hemorrhage and intracerebral hemorrhage.
Intracerebral hemorrhage is bleeding into the brain parenchyma.
It most often stems from the spontaneous rupture of Charcot-Bouchard aneurysms of small vessels damaged by chronic hypertension (see Fig. 63-2).
Thus, pregnancy-associated hemorrhagic strokes such as the one shown in Figure 63-3 are often associated with chronic hypertension and superimposed preeclampsia (Cunningham, 2005; Martin, 2005).
Because of its location, this type of hemorrhage has much higher morbidity and mortality rates than subarachnoid hemorrhage .
Pressure-induced rupture causes bleeding into the putamen, thalamus, adjacent white matter, pons, and cerebellum.
In the 28 women described by Martin and associates (2005), half died and most survivors had permanent disabilities.
This underscores proper management of gestational hypertension, especially systolic hypertension.
Figure 63-3.
A noncontrast computed tomography axial head image demonstrates a large intraparenchymal hemorrhage in this woman with preeclampsia.
Subarachnoid Hemorrhage In a study of 639 cases of pregnancy-related subarachnoid hemorrhage from the Nationwide Inpatient Sample, the incidence was 8.5 per 100,000 pregnancies .
A remarkably similar incidence was reported in Japanese women .
These bleeding events are more likely caused by an underlying cerebrovascular malformation in an otherwise normal patient (see Fig. 63-2).
Ruptured saccular or “berry” aneurysms cause 80 percent of all subarachnoid hemorrhages .
The remaining cases stem from a ruptured AVM, coagulopathy, angiopathy, venous thrombosis, infection, drug abuse, tumors, or trauma.
The mortality rate of subarachnoid hemorrhage during pregnancy is lower than that reported for nonpregnant women—8 versus 17 percent .
Intracranial Aneurysm.
Approximately 1 to 2 percent of adults have this lesion .
Only a small percentage rupture.
The rate approximates 0.1 percent for aneurysms 10 mm .
Most aneurysms identified during pregnancy arise from the
circle of Willis, and in 20 percent of cases, lesions are multiple.
Pregnancy does not raise the risk for aneurysmal rupture.
However, because of their high population prevalence, they are more likely to cause subarachnoid bleeding than other etiologies (Hirsch, 2009; Tiel Groenestege, 2009).
A systematic review of 44 women with 50 aneurysms in pregnancy reported that 72 percent ruptured during pregnancy, and 78 percent of these did so during the third trimester .
This proclivity for rupture late in pregnancy is reported by others .
The cardinal symptom of aneurysmal rupture leading to subarachnoid hemorrhage is sudden severe headache that is accompanied by visual changes, cranial nerve abnormalities, focal neurological deficits, and altered consciousness.
Signs of meningeal irritation, nausea and vomiting, tachycardia, transient hypertension, low-grade fever, leukocytosis, and proteinuria are typical.
Prompt diagnosis and treatment may prevent potentially lethal complications.
The American Heart Association recommends noncontrast cranial CT imaging as the first diagnostic test, although MR imaging may be superior .
Treatment of subarachnoid hemorrhage includes bed rest, analgesia, neurological monitoring, and strict blood pressure control.
Repair of a potentially accessible aneurysm during pregnancy weighs surgical risks against the risk of recurrent hemorrhage.
At least in nonpregnant patients, the risk of subsequent bleeding with conservative treatment is 20 to 30 percent for the first month and then 3 percent per year.
The risk of rebleeding is highest within the first 24 hours, and recurrent hemorrhage leads to death in 70 percent .
Early repair after the sentinel hemorrhage is accomplished by open craniotomy or endovascular coil placement.
In one systematic review of management in pregnancy, coil embolization yielded lower complication rates than aneurysmal clipping .
For unruptured aneurysms, surgical management resulted in a third fewer complications than no treatment.
For gravidas remote from term, repair without hypotensive anesthesia seems optimal.
For women near term, cesarean delivery followed by aneurysm repair is a consideration.
We have successfully done this in several cases.
For aneurysms repaired before or during pregnancy, most allow vaginal delivery if labor ensues remote from aneurysmal repair.
Problems arise in defining “remote,” and although some recommend 2 months, the time for complete healing is unknown.
For women who survive subarachnoid hemorrhage, but in whom surgical repair is not done, we agree with Cartlidge (2000) and recommend against bearing down and favor cesarean delivery.
Arteriovenous Malformations.
These are congenital focal abnormal conglomerations of dilated arteries and veins with subarteriolar disorganization (see Fig. 63-2).
They lack capillaries and have resultant arteriovenous shunting.
Although unclear, the risk of bleeding during pregnancy may rise with gestational age.
When AVMs bleed, half do so into the subarachnoid space, whereas half are intraparenchymal with subarachnoid extension .
Uncommon, they affect an estimated 0.01 percent of the general population.
Of identified AVM cases in pregnancy, 83 percent ruptured during pregnancy or postpartum, and more than 80 percent of these ruptured in the second or third trimester.
Hemorrhage is associated with poor maternal outcome but does not appear to be more likely during pregnancy.
Although correspondingly rare during pregnancy, AVM bleeding accounted for 17 percent of hemorrhagic strokes in one study .
At Parkland Hospital in a 35-year period and nearly 500,000 births, 62 women had a stroke, and five of these were due to a bleeding AVM (Simolke, 1991; Zofkie, 2018).
Treatment of AVMs in nonpregnant patients is individualized.
No consensus guides whether all accessible lesions should be resected.
Factors include AVM symptoms; its anatomy and size; an associated aneurysm, which is found in up to 60 percent of cases; and especially, prior AVM bleeding.
After hemorrhage, the risk of recurrent bleeding in unrepaired
lesions is 6 to 20 percent within the first year, and 2 to 4 percent per year thereafter (Friedlander, 2007; Smith, 2018).
The mortality rate from a bleeding AVM is 10 to 20 percent.
In pregnancy, the decision to operate is usually based on neurosurgical considerations.
Because of the high risk of recurrent hemorrhage from an unresected or inoperable lesion, we favor cesarean delivery.
Demyelinating Or Degenerative Diseases.
The demyelinating diseases are neurological disorders characterized by immune-mediated focal or patchy destruction of myelin sheaths accompanied by an inflammatory response.
The degenerative diseases are multifactorial and characterized by progressive neuronal death.
# Multiple Sclerosis.
This autoimmune demyelinating disease is second only to trauma as a cause of neurological disability in middle adulthood.
The demyelinating effects stem predominantly from T cell–mediated autoimmune destruction of oligodendrocytes that synthesize myelin.
It has a familial occurrence with an environmental trigger, it affects women twice as often as men, and it usually begins in the 20s and 30s (Cree, 2018; Fang, 2020).
In one study, 0.03 percent of California deliveries were complicated by multiple sclerosis (MS) between 2001 and 2009 .
There are three clinical types of multiple sclerosis: 1. Relapsing MS (RMS) is the initial presentation in 90 percent of affected individuals.
With it, unpredictable recurrent episodes of focal or multifocal neurological dysfunction usually are followed by full recovery.
Over time, however, relapses lead to persistent deficits.
2. Secondary progressive MS (SPMS) is relapsing disease that begins to pursue a progressive downhill course after each relapse.
All patients likely develop this type eventually.
3. Primary progressive MS (PPMS) accounts for 10 percent of cases.
With it, disability gradually progresses from the time of initial diagnosis.
Classic findings of MS include sensory loss, visual symptoms from optic neuritis, weakness, and paresthesias.
Clinical diagnosis is aided by MR imaging and cerebrospinal fluid analysis.
In greater than 95 percent of cases, MR imaging shows characteristic multifocal white-matter plaques that represent discrete areas of demyelination .
Their appearance and extent are less helpful for predicting treatment response.
Figure 63-4.
Magnetic resonance cranial images from a woman with multiple sclerosis.
A. T2weighted axial image shows bright signal abnormalities in white matter (arrows), typical for multiple sclerosis.
B. Sagittal T2-FLAIR image shows periventricular hyperintense lesions (Dawson fingers; arrows) representative of demyelination in multiple sclerosis.
Formerly considered an MS variant, neuromyelitis optica spectrum disorder (NMOSD) is viewed as a distinct autoimmune disease.
Antibodies target astrocytes and lead to autoimmune inflammation of the spinal cord and optic nerve.
Some evidence suggests that pregnancy worsens this disorder .
Multiple Sclerosis in Pregnancy Women with MS experience fewer attacks during pregnancy, but with a significantly greater relapse rate postpartum .
This may be related to higher pregnancy-induced numbers of T-helper lymphocytes and an increased T2/Tl ratio.
In a metaanalysis of women with more than 1200 pregnancies complicated by MS, their relapse rate was 0.4 per year before pregnancy; 0.26 per year during pregnancy; and 0.7 per year after delivery .
A systematic review reported similar findings .
Factors associated with postpartum relapse include a high relapse rate before pregnancy, relapses during pregnancy, and a high MS disability score .
Breastfeeding has no effect on postpartum relapses (Hellwig, 2015; Portaccio, 2011).
With uncomplicated disease, pregnancy outcomes are usually not adversely affected (Bove, 2014; Fong, 2018).
Some women may fatigue more easily, those with bladder dysfunction are predisposed to urinary infection, and women with spinal lesions at or above T6 are at risk for autonomic dysreflexia.
In one study of 449 pregnancies in affected women, the labor induction rate was
higher, and second-stage labor was longer .
The greater induction rate and elective operations contributed to the overall higher cesarean delivery rate.
In an analysis of 649 affected women, the mean birthweight was lower, but the perinatal mortality rate was similar to controls .
In a study of 3875 pregnancies in women with MS, risks for infections and preterm delivery were increased .
Management Goals in pregnancy are to arrest acute or initial attacks, employ diseasemodifying agents, and provide symptomatic relief.
Some treatments may require modification during pregnancy.
Acute or initial attacks are treated with high-dose intravenous methylprednisolone—500 to 1000 mg daily for 3 to 5 days.
This is followed by oral prednisone for 2 weeks.
Plasma exchange may help those with fulminant attacks resistant to corticosteroid therapy.
Symptomatic relief can be provided by analgesics.
Carbamazepine, phenytoin, or amitriptyline are suitable after the first trimester for neurogenic pain; baclofen, for spasticity; α1-adrenergic blocking agents, for bladder neck relaxation; and cholinergic and anticholinergic drugs, for bladder-contraction stimulation or inhibition, respectively.
Several disease-modifying therapies are now available to treat relapsing MS or for exacerbations.
Examples include interferons, glatiramer, fingolimod, dimethyl fumarate, natalizumab, and ocrelizumab (Cree, 2018; Tintore, 2019).
Data regarding their safety in pregnancy are limited .
In 246 women with MS, glatiramer was not teratogenic to their offspring .
In a review of 92 pregnancies, first-trimester natalizumab exposure was associated with an increased miscarriage risk .
Fetal exposure in 89 pregnancies to fingolimod was associated with six fetal malformations and nine spontaneous losses.
Because of this and associated animal teratogenicity, its use in pregnancy is not recommended.
Due to its prolonged persistence, contraception is recommended for 2 months after fingolimod cessation .
Last, prevention of relapses postpartum has been reported with intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG).
A dose of 0.4 g/kg is given daily for 5 days during weeks 1, 6, and 12 .
# Myasthenia Gravis.
This autoimmune-mediated neuromuscular disorder is more common in women, and its incidence peaks in their 20s and 30s .
The etiology is unknown, but genetic factors likely play a role.
Of affected patients, 80 to 90 percent demonstrate antibodies to the acetylcholine receptor .
Those that are seronegative often have antibodies to muscle-specific tyrosine kinase (MuSK), which regulates assembly of the acetylcholine receptor subunits at the neuromuscular junction.
Cardinal features of myasthenia are weakness and easy fatigability of facial, oropharyngeal, extraocular, and limb muscles.
Deep-tendon reflexes are preserved.
Cranial muscles are involved early and disparately, and diplopia and ptosis are common.
Facial muscle weakness causes difficulty in smiling, chewing, and speaking.
In 85 percent of patients, the weakness becomes generalized.
Other autoimmune diseases may coexist, and hypothyroidism should be excluded.
The clinical course is marked by exacerbations.
These can be life threatening and include myasthenic crises, which are characterized by severe muscle weakness, inability to swallow, and respiratory muscle paralysis .
Another is a cholinergic crisis, which is caused by excessive cholinergic medication and leads to nausea, vomiting, muscle weakness, abdominal pain, and diarrhea.
Management Myasthenia gravis is manageable but not curable.
The oral anticholinesterase pyridostigmine (Mestinon) is first-line treatment.
Thymectomy is recommended but postponed until after pregnancy (Amato, 2018a; Wolfe, 2019).
Anticholinesterase medications improve symptoms by impeding acetylcholine degradation but seldom produce normal muscle function.
Ironically, overdose is manifest by the cholinergic crisis mentioned earlier and may be difficult to differentiate from myasthenic symptoms.
Most gravidas refractory to anticholinesterase therapy respond to immunosuppressive therapy with
glucocorticoids, azathioprine, or cyclosporine.
When short-term, rapid improvement is needed—such as for a surgical procedure or a myasthenic crisis—high-dose IVIG or plasma exchange is usually effective (Amato, 2018a; Sanders, 2016).
Myasthenia Gravis and Pregnancy The greatest period of risk is within the first year following diagnosis.
Thus, postponing pregnancy until improvement is sustained is reasonable.
Antepartum management of myasthenia gravis includes close observation, liberal rest, and prompt treatment of infection .
Women in remission who become pregnant while taking corticosteroids or azathioprine should continue these.
Acute onset or exacerbation of myasthenia gravis demands prompt hospitalization and supportive care.
Plasmapheresis and high-dose IVIG are options for emergencies .
In refractory cases, thymectomy has been successfully performed during pregnancy.
Although pregnancy does not appear to affect the overall course of myasthenia gravis, fatigue common to most pregnancies may be exacerbated, and the expanding uterus may compromise respiration.
Maternal hypotension or hypovolemia are ideally avoided because they can trigger crises.
The clinical course of myasthenia gravis during pregnancy is unpredictable, and frequent hospitalizations are the norm.
Up to a third of women have worsening symptoms during pregnancy, and exacerbations develop equally in all three trimesters (Djelmis, 2002; Podciechowski, 2005).
In women with stable disease, most will remain stable throughout pregnancy but likely worsen in the first few months postpartum .
Myasthenia gravis has no significant adverse effects on pregnancy outcomes .
Preeclampsia is a concern because magnesium sulfate may precipitate a severe myasthenia crisis (Hamaoui, 2009; Heaney, 2010).
Although phenytoin use also is problematic in this regard, its adverse effects are less troublesome.
Because smooth muscle is unaffected, most women have normal labor.
Oxytocin is given for the usual indications, and cesarean delivery is reserved for obstetrical indications.
Narcotics may cause respiratory depression, and close observation and respiratory support are essential during labor and delivery.
Curariform drugs are avoided.
Examples include magnesium sulfate, muscle relaxants used with general anesthesia, and aminoglycosides.
Neuraxial analgesia is accomplished with amide-type local agents.
Regional analgesia is preferred unless bulbar involvement or respiratory compromise is significant (Almeida, 2010; Blichfeldt-Lauridsen, 2012).
During secondstage labor, some women may have impaired voluntary expulsive efforts that may warrant operative vaginal delivery.
Neonatal Effects As discussed, 80 percent of mothers with myasthenia gravis have immunoglobulin G (IgG) antibodies against the acetylcholine receptor.
These and anti-MuSK antibodies cross transplacentally, and the fetus can be affected.
Poor fetal swallowing may yield hydramnios .
Similarly, 10 to 20 percent of neonates manifest myasthenia symptoms .
Transient symptoms usually include a feeble cry, poor suckling, and respiratory distress.
Symptoms usually respond to anticholinesterase agents and resolve within a few weeks as maternal IgG antibodies clear.
Neuropathies.
Peripheral neuropathy is a general term for peripheral nerve(s) disorders, in which one or more nerves are affected.
Mononeuropathies are relatively common in pregnancy and signify focal involvement of a single nerve trunk.
These imply local causation such as trauma, compression, or entrapment.
For example, traumatic pudendal, obturator, femoral, and common fibular mononeuropathies can stem from childbirth .
Polyneuropathies can be axonal or demyelinating and can be acute, subacute, or chronic .
These are often associated with systemic diseases such as diabetes, with drug or environmental toxin exposure, or with genetic disease.
Late-stage syphilis is a rare cause .
# Guillain–Barré Syndrome.
In 75 percent of cases, this acute demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy has clinical or serological evidence of an acute infection.
Common
associated infections are Campylobacter jejuni, cytomegalovirus, Zika virus, and Epstein-Barr virus; surgical procedures; and immunizations .
Guillain–Barré syndrome is thought to be immune-mediated from antibodies formed against nonself antigens.
Demyelination causes sensory and motor conduction blockade, and remyelination yields recovery in most cases.
Clinical features include an areflexic, ascending paralysis, with or without sensory disturbances.
Autonomic dysfunction is common.
The full syndrome develops over 1 to 3 weeks.
Some manifest as chronic inflammatory demyelinating polyneuropathy, and our experiences indicate that this may be relatively common in these young women.
Guillain-Barré syndrome is not more common in pregnancy, and its clinical course mirrors that for nonpregnant individuals.
After an insidious onset, paresis and paralysis most often continue to ascend to cause ventilatory weakness.
Management is supportive and incorporates venous thromboembolism prophylaxis, pressure ulcer prevention, and enteral nutrition.
In the worsening phase, patients are hospitalized, and a fourth require ventilatory assistance.
IVIG or plasmapheresis are beneficial if begun within 1 to 2 weeks of motor symptoms, but neither decreases mortality rates .
Up to 10 percent of patients deteriorate after initial improvement on therapy, and re-treatment with 2 g/kg IVIG over 5 days is recommended.
Although most patients recover fully within several months to a year, the mortality rate is 5 percent, mainly due to pulmonary complications and arrhythmias .
# Bell Palsy.
This disfiguring palsy is usually a mononeuropathic acute facial paralysis that is relatively common in reproductive-aged women .
It has a female predominance, and rates in pregnancy may be increased (Beal, 2018; Choi, 2020).
The disease is characterized by facial nerve inflammation and often is associated with reactivation of herpes simplex virus or herpes zoster virus.
Other causes are Lyme disease and borreliosis.
Figure 63-5.
Bell facial nerve palsy developing on the day of cesarean delivery for dichorionic twins.
This woman was treated with prednisone and antiviral medication, and 3 weeks postpartum, the palsy had almost resolved.
Bell palsy usually has an abrupt and painful onset with maximum weakness by 48 hours.
In some cases, hyperacusis and loss of taste accompany paralysis .
Management includes supportive care with facial muscle massage and eye protection against corneal injury from drying.
Consensus supports that prednisone, 1 mg/kg given orally daily for 5 days, will improve outcomes and shorten the recovery period (Beal, 2018; Madhok, 2016).
It is controversial whether added valacyclovir or acyclovir will hasten recovery (Beal, 2018; Gagyor, 2019).
It is unclear if pregnancy alters the prognosis for spontaneous facial palsy recovery.
In one study, compared with 90 percent of nonpregnant women and men, only half of pregnant women recovered to a satisfactory level after 1 year .
In another report, pregnancy-associated Bell palsy had worse long-term outcomes compared with those of nonpregnant cohort .
Some prognostic markers for incomplete recovery are bilateral palsy, recurrence in a subsequent pregnancy, greater percentage of nerve function loss, and a faster rate of loss (Cohen, 2000; Gilden, 2004).
Other than a fivefold greater rate for gestational hypertension or preeclampsia, women with Bell palsy do not have increased adverse pregnancy outcomes rates .
# Carpal Tunnel Syndrome.
This syndrome results from compression of the median nerve and is the most frequent mononeuropathy in pregnancy .
Symptoms include burning, numbness, or tingling along the inner half of one or both hands.
Others are wrist pain and numbness extending into the forearm and sometimes into the shoulder.
Symptoms are bilateral in 80 percent of gravidas, and 10 percent have evidence for severe denervation.
Differential diagnosis includes cervical radiculopathy of C6–C7 and de Quervain tendonitis.
The latter is caused by swelling of the conjoined tendons and their sheaths
near the distal radius.
Nerve conduction studies may help to clarify.
In pregnancy, the reported incidence of carpal tunnel syndrome is 7 to 43 percent and varies greatly because the range of symptoms is marked (Meems, 2015; Oliveira, 2019).
Symptomatic treatment with a splint applied to a slightly flexed wrist during sleep lightens pressure and usually provides relief.
Although symptoms typically are self-limited, occasionally surgical decompression and corticosteroid injections are necessary (Keith, 2009; Shi, 2011).
Symptoms may persist in more than half of patients at 1 year and in a third at 3 years .
Meralgia paresthetica is another common pregnancy-induced compression neuropathy .
Compression of the lateral femoral cutaneous nerve creates pain, burning, and numbness on the outside of the thigh.
For treatment, the site at which the nerve crosses the crease in the groin can be injected with corticosteroids.
Oral gabapentin is another treatment.
Spinal Cord Injury.
According to the National Spinal Cord Injury Statistical Center (2021), approximately 18,000 new spinal cord injuries are sustained each year.
The average age is 42 years, and males account for 80 percent of new cases.
Cord injury severity determines the short- and long-term prognosis and pregnancy prognosis.
For women, many have altered sexual function and transient hypothalamic pituitary hypogonadism.
Despite this, pregnancy is not uncommon, and in a review of nearly 2000 women, 2 percent reported pregnancy in the prior 12 months .
Two serious and life-threatening events can complicate spinal cord injuries.
First, if the cord is transected above T10, the cough reflex is impaired, respiratory function may be compromised, and pneumonitis from covert aspiration can be serious.
Pulmonary function tests are considered to assess this risk, and some women may need ventilatory support in late pregnancy or labor.
Second, women with lesions above T5–T6 are at risk for autonomic dysreflexia.
With this, stimuli from structures innervated below the level of the spinal lesion lead to massive, disordered sympathetic stimulation.
Abrupt catecholamine release can prompt vasoconstriction with severe hypertension and symptoms that include throbbing headaches, facial flushing, sweating, bradycardia, tachycardia, arrhythmias, and respiratory distress.
Dysreflexia can be precipitated by various stimuli.
These include distention or manipulation of reproductive tract or lower urinary tract organs or bowel (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2020; Krassioukov, 2009).
In one report, 12 of 15 women at risk for autonomic dysreflexia suffered at least one episode during pregnancy .
Gravidas with spinal cord injury have an increased frequency of other complications.
In a review of 37 affected pregnant women, 30 percent had pyelonephritis, 32 percent had lower urinary tract infections, and 9 percent had pressure sores .
Two women developed autonomic dysreflexia, which caused cerebral hemorrhage in one.
Urinary infections may be related to altered vaginal microbiota .
Bowel dysfunction causes constipation in more than half, and anemia and pressurenecrosis skin lesions are common.
Vaginal delivery is generally successful .
Operative vaginal delivery is frequently necessary.
Because uterine contractions are not affected by spinal cord lesions, labor is usually easy, comparatively painless, and at times precipitous.
If the lesion is below T12, uterine contractions are felt normally.
For lesions above T12, the risk of out-ofhospital delivery is substantial and can be minimized by teaching women to palpate for uterine contractions.
This is especially important because up to 20 percent of women deliver preterm .
Some recommend tocodynamometry and weekly cervical examinations beginning at 28 to 30 weeks’ gestation.
Another reasonable option that we frequently employ at Parkland Hospital is elective hospitalization after 36 to 37 weeks.
Spinal or epidural analgesia extending to T10 prevents autonomic dysreflexia and should be instituted at the start of labor .
If severe
symptoms are identified before epidural placement, steps are taken to abolish the provoking stimulus.
A parenteral antihypertensive agent such as hydralazine or labetalol is given.
Idiopathic Intracranial Hypertension.
Also known as pseudotumor cerebri, this disorder is typified by increased intracranial pressure without hydrocephalus.
The cause is unknown, but it may result from overproduction or underabsorption of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), or both.
Symptoms include headache in at least 90 percent of cases, visual disturbances such as loss of a visual field or central visual acuity in 70 percent, and commonly occurring papilledema that may be sightthreatening (Heaney, 2010; Kesler, 2013).
Other complaints are stiff neck, back pain, pulsatile tinnitus, and cranial nerve palsies .
The syndrome is often found in young women and is prevalent in those who are obese, who recently gained weight, or both .
Along with symptoms, other criteria for diagnosis include elevated intracranial pressure >25 cm H2O, normal CSF composition, normal cranial CT or MR imaging findings, papilledema, and no evidence for systemic disease.
If papilledema is not present, other criteria are required .
Idiopathic intracranial hypertension is usually self-limited, but long-term vision loss is common .
Visual defects can be prevented by lowering the CSF pressure, and agents include acetazolamide to reduce fluid production, furosemide, or topiramate.
Corticosteroids are now rarely used.
Surgical intervention is occasionally necessary and is accomplished by either lumboperitoneal shunting of spinal fluid or optic nerve sheath fenestration.
Another treatment is stenting of dural venous sinus stenosis .
It is controversial if pregnancy is a risk factor for idiopathic intracranial hypertension.
Certainly, symptoms may first appear in pregnancy, and women previously diagnosed may become symptomatic.
Symptoms usually develop by midpregnancy, tend to be self-limited, and usually resolve postpartum.
Pregnancy does not alter management.
Some recommend serial visualfield testing to forestall permanent vision loss.
In a report of 16 pregnant women, visual-field loss developed in four, and it became permanent in one .
Visual-field loss is often coincident with the development of papilledema, for which acetazolamide is given.
Lee and associates (2005) reported successful treatment of 12 pregnant women.
Although outmoded for treatment of nonpregnant individuals, repeated lumbar punctures are generally successful in providing temporary relief throughout pregnancy.
In some pregnant women, surgical therapy becomes necessary, including optic nerve sheath fenestration .
Pregnancy complications are likely due to associated obesity and not to intracranial hypertension.
Rates of adverse maternal and perinatal outcomes are not increased .
The route of delivery depends on obstetrical indications, and conduction analgesia is safe (Aly, 2007; Karmaniolou, 2011).
Maternal Ventricular Shunts.
Pregnancies in women with previously placed ventricular shunts for obstructive hydrocephalus usually have satisfactory outcomes.
Shunts may be ventriculoperitoneal, ventriculoatrial, or ventriculopleural.
Partial obstruction of a shunt is common, especially late in pregnancy .
In one report of 17 such pregnancies, neurological complications were reported in 13 .
Findings included headaches in 60 percent, nausea and vomiting in 35 percent, lethargy in 30 percent, and ataxia or gaze paresis, each in 20 percent.
Most symptoms respond to conservative management.
However, if CT scanning during symptom evaluation discloses acute hydrocephaly, the shunt is tapped or pumped several times daily.
In some cases, surgical revision is necessary and may be emergently indicated .
Another shunting procedure is placement of an endoscopic third ventriculostomy for hydrocephalus.
With this, a small hole is created in the floor of the third ventricle to allow CSF to flow directly into lower cisterns.
One report described successful results in five gravidas who underwent endoscopic ventriculostomy .
Vaginal
delivery is preferred in women with shunts, and unless there is a meningomyelocele, conduction analgesia is permitted.
Antimicrobial prophylaxis is indicated if the peritoneal cavity is entered for cesarean delivery or puerperal sterilization.
Maternal Brain Death.
Brain death is rare in obstetrics, and only a few institutional brain-death policies address pregnancy .
Life-support systems and parenteral alimentation for up to 20 weeks while awaiting delivery have been described (Hussein, 2006; Powner, 2003; Reinhold, 2019).
Some women were treated with aggressive tocolysis and antimicrobial therapy.
In one review of 17 women with persistent vegetative state who were given various levels of support, five women died after delivery, and most of the others remained in their vegetative state .
The ethical, financial, and legal implications, both civil and criminal, that arise from providing or withdrawing such care are profound .
In some women, perimortem cesarean delivery is performed.